Ideally, we try to center our diets around
healthy, unprocessed plant foods.
But in today's world,
most of what fills our grocery
carts isn't just processed,
but ultra-processed,
which is good for shelf life,
but not necessarily our life.
Let's take a closer look.
"What Are Ultra-Processed Foods?"
Modern nutrition science
began about a century ago
in the context
of nutrient deficiency diseases.
Editorials in the Journal of
the American Medical Association
had titles like "Sugar as Food,"
heralding sugar
as one of the cheapest sources
of calories.
For six cents, you could
buy three thousand calories.
But the Nutrient Deficiency era
gave way
to the Dietary Excess era.
No longer were we dying
of nutrient deficiency diseases
like scurvy as much
as we were dying
from nutrient excess diseases
like obesity and heart disease.
So, nutrition science
became more
about avoiding
too many calories,
too much saturated fat,
too much sugar,
and too much sodium,
while still focused
on nutrients.
This allowed food companies
to get away with whipping out
fiber-fortified Froot Loops.
But "Food, Not Nutrients, is the
Fundamental Unit of Nutrition."
And to its credit,
the field of nutrition
started moving
towards a more holistic view.
First generation
dietary guidelines
emphasized individual nutrients,
then moved to second generation
food-based dietary guidelines,
which largely converged
on encouraging diets
rich in vegetables,
fruits, legumes
(beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils),
whole grains, and nuts.
But an area
of emerging importance
is the degree
of food processing.
National nutrition guidelines
first told us
to cut down on saturated fat,
alcohol, cholesterol,
salt, and sugar.
Then they started actually
naming names,
suggesting citizens might want
to cut down on cake,
for example.
So, from nutrients to foods,
and more recently,
countries recommending
limiting processed foods.
This was the bombshell
that really started
the momentum,
a commentary in the journal
Public Health Nutrition in 2009
by Carlos Monteiro,
a nutrition professor
at the University of Sao Paulo.
Maybe the issue
with nutrition and health
is not so much the food,
nor the nutrients,
as much as the level
of processing.
For example,
food-based dietary guidelines
might tell us
to eat more vegetable soup.
Great! But there’s
vegetable soup,
then there’s vegetable soup.
Are we talking about
cleaning-out-your-fridge
vegetable soup?
A health-haloed organic quinoa
and kale soup
with a heart-stopping
1,200 milligrams of sodium
per can?
How about a vegetable soup
that has more salt
than it has vegetables?
Or a vegetable flavored soup
that contains
more artificial flavors and MSG
than it has vegetables.
Just like there
is breakfast cereal
and then there
is breakfast cereal.
Professor Monteiro
and colleagues
proposed the "NOVA"
food classification system.
NOVA is not an acronym.
It means new in Portuguese,
as in a new way
to classify foods,
based on the level
of processing.
NOVA classifies all foods
and food products
into four groups.
Group 1 foods are unprocessed
or minimally processed,
like fresh, dried,
frozen, or cooked plants
or animal parts, with nothing
bad added, like salt or sugar.
Group 2 foods are the salt,
sugar, and fats used in cooking,
and Group 3 includes
traditionally processed foods,
like when you add
Group 2 ingredients
to Group 1 foods.
But what really put NOVA
on the map is Group 4,
its concept
of ultra-processed foods.
These are
industrial formulations
of several ingredients which,
besides salt, sugar,
oils and fats,
include food substances not used
in culinary preparations,
like added flavors, colors,
artificial sweeteners,
emulsifiers, and other additives
used to imitate real foods.
Like a frosted grape pop-tart
that has more grapes on
the front of the box
than inside it,
with less grapes than salt,
but may artificially
taste like grapes
and look like grapes
because of one,
two, three, four,
five different food dyes.
"Simply put, ultra-processed
foods are foods
that can’t be made
in home kitchens
because they have
been chemically
or physically transformed
using industrial processes."
"They typically contain
little or no whole foods,
are ready-to-consume or heat up,
and are fatty, salty,
or sugary
and depleted in dietary fiber,"
and other nutrients-
like all the sweet,
fatty, or salty snacks
like potato chips, ice cream,
soda, candy, French fries,
burgers, hot dogs,
chicken nuggets,
fish sticks.
Basically, almost everything
in a box or a bag.
Why not just call them,
"Packaged foods"?
Well, they were
thinking about it,
but were afraid consumers
might look at a bag of apples
or something and get confused.
Before the NOVA classification
system was introduced,
the issue of food processing
was largely ignored,
or minimized,
in education and outreach,
as well as in public
health policies.
But NOVA exploded
onto the stage,
resulting in a super-NOVA
in the world of nutrition.
But what exactly
is so revolutionary
about this concept
of ultra-processed foods?
I mean, wasn’t fatty, salty,
sugary junk always a bad idea?
What’s so new about NOVA?
Monteiro suggests
that there are harmful effects
of ultra-processed foods
that are independent
of their nutrient profile.
Is that true?
That’s exactly what
I’ll cover next.